<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
%entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.startersystem.prepare">
 <title>Preparation</title>
 <para></para>
 <sect1 id="cha.startersystem.prepare.first">
  <title>Preparing to install the &starts;</title>
  <para>
   The &starter; is a pre-built installation server for &slesz; that can be
   installed on your z/VM system using CMS tools, eliminating the need for
   coordinating access to a separate Linux or UNIX system elsewhere on your
   network.  It minimizizes the impact of network-based installation on your
   internal and external networks.
  </para>
  <para>
   The &starts; consists of:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Utilities and configuration tools for installation of the &starts; from a
     CMS terminal session
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Compressed disk images of the &starts;, including a complete set of RPM
     packages as shipped with the SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for System z
     release.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Utilities and configuration tools to assist with installation of
     additional Linux virtual machines from the &starts; installation
     server. The configuration tools package also includes a "rescue" system
     that can be used to recover a SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for System z
     virtual machine if there are problems that prevent the server from
     booting and connecting to the network for normal maintenance.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   This document describes the parts you need to download and the resources
   required to install the &starts;. The instructions also include an example
   of how to install an additional Linux server from the &starts;.
  </para>
  <warning>
   <title>THE STARTER SYSTEM IS NOT SUITABLE FOR GENERAL USE</title>
   <para>
    The &starts; image has been highly customized for use as an installation
    server for other SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for System z based Linux
    servers running in virtual machines. The &starts; is NOT suitable for
    general use and you should not attempt to use it for any other purpose.
   </para>
  </warning>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="cha.startersystem.prepare.second">
  <title>What you will need</title>
  <para>
   To install the &starts;, you will need to ensure you have sufficient
   resources available on your system to complete the installation and obtain
   two CMS tools and the &starts; disk images from the Internet.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
