<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
%entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.startersystem.configure">
 <title>Configuring the &starts;</title>
 <abstract>
  <para>
   The starter system is almost completely configured, however some
   information about your local network needs to be supplied in order to
   properly connect and be usable.
  </para>
 </abstract>
 <sect1 id="sec.startersystem.configure.first">
  <title>Configuring Network Connectivity</title>
  <para>
   Log into NOVSTART via a tn3270 session and press RETURN to interrupt the
   boot process of the Linux system. If a terminal is connected to the guest
   VM the startup profile will wait 10 seconds to give the user a chance to
   interrupt the boot of the linux system.
  </para>
  <para>
   Please execute the command <screen>NETNEW NETWORK PARMS</screen> to enter
   the values of a new installed system and also if values of an existing
   system should be modified.
  </para>
  <screen>NETNEW NETWORK PARMS A
  System:  Welcome to the SUSE Linux Enterprise Server Starter System
           configuration tool.

           You didn't specify all the necessary values in NETWORK PARMS A,
           so I have to ask you for those now.

           Will the starter system be using a DHCP server to get its IP
           address? (Y/N)
  You:     <emphasis role="bold">N</emphasis>
  System:  Please enter the IP address for the starter system.
  You:     <emphasis role="bold">192.168.1.100</emphasis>
  System:  Please enter the network mask for the subnet to which the
           starter system will be connected.
           For class c networks, this would be 255.255.255.0,
           For class b networks, it would be 255.255.0.0, etc.
  You:     <emphasis role="bold">255.255.255.0</emphasis>
  System:  Please enter the IP address of the default gateway for the
           starter system.
  You:     <emphasis role="bold">192.168.1.1</emphasis>
  System:  Please enter the IP address of the DNS server the
           starter system will use.
  You:     <emphasis role="bold">10.10.0.1</emphasis>
  System:  Please enter the host name you want the starter system to have.
           Note that this may _not_ include the domain name.
  You:     <emphasis role="bold">novstart</emphasis>
  System:  Please enter the domain name for the starter system.
           Note that this must be at least two levels of qualification
           but it can be more, based on your site standards.
  You:     <emphasis role="bold">example.com</emphasis>
  System:  Is your network interface in layer 2 mode? (Y/N)
  You:     <emphasis role="bold">n</emphasis>
  System:  Here are the values you've specified.  Please review them and
           indicate if you want to revise any of them or finish generating
           the output file.
             Host name       novstart
             Domain name     example.com
             IP address      192.168.1.100
             Network mask    255.255.255.0
             Default gateway 192.168.1.1
             DNS server      10.10.0.1
             DHCP            N
             Layer2          N
 
           Please select modify or accept
           1 = Modify
           2 = Accept
  You:     <emphasis role="bold">2</emphasis>
  System:  Now that you're satisfied with your network parameters, it's time
           to write them out to disk. Do you want to over-write your
           input file NETWORK PARMS A, or do you want to write to a new file?
 
           1 = Over-write NETWORK PARMS A
           2 = Write to a new file
           3 = Exit without writing anything
  You:     <emphasis role="bold">1</emphasis>
  System:  1
           OK, writing over NETWORK PARMS A it is!
           Blam!
           Ready; T=0.01/0.01 13:11:46</screen>
  <para>
   <!-- "pagebreak" --><?dbfo-need height="15em"?>
   After all questions are answered, please enter the following command to
   start the &starts;:
  </para>
  <screen>IPL 150 CLEAR</screen>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.startersystem.configure.second">
  <title>Other NOVSTART Maintenance Tasks</title>
  <sect2 id="sec.startersystem.configure.second.first">
   <title>Changing the NOVSTART root password</title>
   <para>
    The starter system is shipped with a default password of "novell" and
    should be changed immediately after installation.  To change the password:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Log in to the systen via ssh as root using a SSH client such as putty.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Use the <command>passwd</command> command to change the password.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sec.startersystem.configure.second.third">
 <title>Recovering from a damaged or misconfigured system</title>
  <para>
   If you need to change the network configuration of the starter system,
   connect via a tn3270 session to NOVSTART.  Log in as root and issue the
   following commands:
  </para>
  <screen>rm /etc/Startsysten_already_configured
reboot</screen>
  <para>
   Now the system reboots and read in the parameters from the file
   <filename>NETWORK PARMS</filename>.
  </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
