<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
%entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.startersystem.client_install">
 <title>Installing a New Linux Guest from the Starter System</title>
 <para/>
 <sect1 id="sec.startersystem.client_install.first">
  <title>Installing a New Guest from the Starter System</title>
  <para>
   Now that you have the starter system installed, you can use it to install
   additional virtual Linux servers quickly and easily without need for an
   external installation media server.
  </para>
  <para>
   The directions in this section describe how to install additional servers
   using the starter system as a source.
  </para>
  <sect2 id="sec.startersystem.client_install.second.first">
   <title>CP Directory Entry Notes</title>
   <para>
    When creating a new virtual server, the CLIENT SAMPDIR file on NOVSTART
    19F can be used as a template CP directory entry. CLIENT SAMPDIR defines a
    basic set of virtual machine options and devices and can be used as a
    basic convention for installing all your virtual servers.
   </para>
   <para>
    The CLIENT SAMPDIR file supplied with the starter system is shown in <xref
    linkend="sec.startersystem.client_install.second.second"/>.
   </para>
   <screen>USER NOVSTART PASSWORD 512M 512M G
*
*  Sample Linux virtual Server CP directory entry
*
*  The following statements define the virtual machine console,
*  processor, machine mode and spooled unit record devices
*  simulated by z/VM
*
   IPL CMS PARM AUTOCR
   MACHINE XA 2
   CPU 0
   CPU 1
   CONSOLE 0009 3215 T CONLOG
   SPOOL 000C 2540 READER *
   SPOOL 000D 2540 PUNCH A
   SPOOL 000E 1403 A
*
*  These statements link important components for use by
*  CMS during IPL
*
   LINK MAINT 0190 0190 RR
   LINK MAINT 019E 019E RR
   LINK MAINT 019D 019D RR
*
*  This statement links the starter system setup tools for
*  use during Linux installation
*
   LINK NOVSTART 019F 019F RR
*
*  This statement defines a virtual network adapter for the
*  virtual machine. This example shows defining the connection to
*  a guest LAN in the CP directory entry if you so desire.
*
   NICDEF 0340 TYPE QDIO LAN SYSTEM GLAN1
*
*  These statements show examples of minidisk definitions for the
*  new virtual machine. The last token on each line is the CP label
*  of the DASD that will contain the minidisk. These should be
*  allocated using your local CP directory management process.
*
*  MDISK 0191 3390 0001 0005 USER01 MR RIAMSL WIAMSL MIAMSL
*  MDISK 019F 3390 0006 0050 USER01 MR ALL    WIAMSL MIAMSL
*  MDISK 0150 3390 0056 3283 USER01 MR RIAMSL WIAMSL MIAMSL
*  MDISK 0151 3390 0001 3338 USER02 MR RIAMSL WIAMSL MIAMSL
*  MDISK 0F00 3390 0001 3338 TEMP01 MR RIAMSL WIAMSL MIAMSL</screen>
   <para>
    The CLIENT SAMPDIR file defines the following options:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>2 virtual CPUs</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>512M virtual storage</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      One virtual NIC at address 340. You will need to update the NICDEF to
      reflect the guest LAN or VSWITCH to which you wish to connect the
      network adapter. For initial installation, it should be the same VSWITCH
      or guest LAN to which you attached the starter system. You may need to
      grant access to the VSWITCH or guest LAN via the GRANT command if you do
      not use a ESM to control access permissions.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A link to NOVSTART 19F (installation and helpful operations tools)
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>A link to MAINT 190 (for use by CMS)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Comments on recommended minidisk sizes and virtual address patterns.
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>0191 (for CMS startup and configuration use)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>0150-015F (Linux disks)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>0160-016F (Swap space, created via DEFINE VDISK or SWAPGEN)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>0170-017F (Additional Linux disks if needed)</para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
     <para>
      Actual minidisks should be added using your local directory maintenance
      procedures.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    NOVSTART 19F also contains some helpful tools for starting the
    installation process:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>SLES</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Run this EXEC to send the standard installation kernel text decks to
       the virtual reader of the new guest and IPL from the virtual
       reader. This EXEC should be run from the new virtual machine you are
       installing.
      </para>
      <para>
       The SLES exec can also be used to start a damaged system to effect
       repairs.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>SWAPGEN</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       SWAPGEN provides a simple method of formatting and utilizing virtual
       disk in memory (VDISK) for Linux swap space.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    These tools should be available to all Linux guests installed from the
    starter system.
   </para>
   <!-- "pagebreak" --><?dbfo-need height="15em"?>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sec.startersystem.client_install.second.second">
   <title>Starting the Install Process</title>
   <para>To start the installation, follow these steps:</para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Create a new z/VM userid based on CLIENT SAMPDIR (as described above).
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Log in as the new z/VM userid via tn3270.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Format the minidisk at virtual address 0191 by typing:</para>
     <screen>FORMAT 191 A</screen>
     <para>The label of the minidisk is not important.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Access NOVSTART 19F by typing ACCESS 19F Q</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Copy the sample PROFILE EXEC from NOVSTART 19F by typing:
     </para>
     <screen>COPYFILE PROFILE SAMPEXEC Q PROFILE EXEC A</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Start the installation process by typing <command>SLES</command>
     </para>
     <para>The install process will begin.</para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    The remainder of the installation process will proceed as described in the
    Novell documentation.  You should respond to the prompts similar to the
    following:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>Select 4) Start Installation of System</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Select 1) Start Installation or Update</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Select 2) Network</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select your desired installation method (see <xref
      linkend="sec.startersystem.client_install.second.third"/>)
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Select 1) OSA-2 or OSA Express as the network device.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Select 1) QDIO</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Select 1) Ethernet</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      When prompted, enter the OSA address information. For servers based on
      CLIENT SAMPDIR, these values should be:
     </para>
     <informaltable frame="topbot" rowsep="2">
      <tgroup cols="2" colsep="1">
       <colspec colnum="1" colname="1" colwidth="50*"/>
       <colspec colnum="2" colname="2" colwidth="50*"/>
       <tbody>
        <row>
         <entry colname="1"><para>Channel ID</para></entry>
         <entry colname="2"><para>Value</para></entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry colname="1"><para>Read</para></entry>
         <entry colname="2"><para>0.0.0340</para></entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry colname="1"><para>Write</para></entry>
         <entry colname="2"><para>0.0.0341</para></entry>
        </row>
        <row>
         <entry colname="1"><para>Data</para></entry>
         <entry colname="2"><para>0.0.0342</para></entry>
        </row>
       </tbody>
      </tgroup>
     </informaltable> 
     <para>
      A port name is not necessary for virtual NICs.Enabling layer 2 support
      should reflect the definition of the guest LAN or VSWITCH to which the
      new server is connected.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Specify the network address of the starter system server as the
      installation source.  See <xref
      linkend="sec.startersystem.client_install.second.third"/>.  method.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sec.startersystem.client_install.second.third">
   <title>Specifying the Install Server Address and Install Method</title>
   <para>
    The starter system provides NFS, FTP, SMB and HTTP-based installation
    support. When prompted for the address of the installation source, supply
    the IP address of the starter system virtual machine.
   </para>
   <para>
    You may choose any of the supported installation methods; all work equally
    well over the internal network provided by a guest LAN or VSWITCH.
   </para>
   <para>
    Each installation method will require some additional information about
    how to locate the data used by that method. The following table describes
    additional parameters used by that method.
   </para>
   <!-- "pagebreak" --><?dbfo-need height="15em"?>
   <informaltable frame="topbot" rowsep="1">
    <tgroup cols="2" colsep="1">
     <colspec colnum="1" colname="1" colwidth="20*"/>
     <colspec colnum="2" colname="2" colwidth="80*"/>
     <tbody>
      <row>
       <entry colname="1"><para>Method</para></entry>
       <entry colname="2"><para>Parameters</para></entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry colname="1"><para>FTP</para></entry>
       <entry colname="2">
        <para>User anonymous, directory is /SLES11/SP4/s390x/DVD1</para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry colname="1"><para>HTTP</para></entry>
       <entry colname="2">
        <para>directory is /SLES11/SP4/s390x/DVD1</para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry colname="1"><para>SMB</para></entry>
       <entry colname="2">
        <para>Workgroup WORKGROUP, share "SLES-STARTER", user guest, directory is /SLES11/SP4/s390x/DVD1</para>
       </entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </informaltable>
   <para>
    No proxy server or application gateway specifications are required if
    using the starter system as the installation source.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sec.startersystem.client_install.second.forth">
   <title>Additional Information About the Install Process</title>
   <para>
    Following the completion of the install process, you will likely be able
    to reduce the amount of virtual storage required by the newly-installed
    virtual machine, although how much reduction is possible will be dictated
    by the applications and features you have installed. Smaller virtual
    machines typically help overall system performance by imposing a smaller
    memory footprint for z/VM to manage.
   </para>
   <para>
    You can add additional software to your installed virtual machine using
    YaST and the starter system as a installation source.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
